RICHA VERMA

Senior Software Engineer | Ex-IBM | Houston, TX | 919-656-6209

richa.verma.kz@gmail.com| linkedin.com/in/richa-verma | github.com/richa-verma1001 | rverma-portfolio

CAREER PROFILE

15 years of fullstack software development experience with IBM; 5 years of experience in frontend stack React, Node.js, Worked as a Technical Lead for 3 key projects at IBM; **Awards:** IBM Outstanding Achievement Award, IBM UX Champion Award; **Patent:** Visual Representation of Erroneous Fields; **Certifications:** PMI Agile Foundations Practitioner

EXPERIENCE

Senior Software Engineer | Technical Lead | IBM | Watson

Aug 2015 - Jun 2018

Led a team of 8 developers, successfully delivering Watson Company Analyzer, an Al powered Saas offering to the IBM cloud platform. Recognized for -

- Facilitating project planning, collaborating with stakeholders refining requirements & prioritizing product backlog.
- Improved user satisfaction, by proactively working with design for early feedback on wireframes & enhancing UI.
- Increased development productivity through the adoption of modern technologies React, Node.js and Docker.
- Providing actionable insights & KPIs to stakeholders with integration of analytics, tracking events & app usage.
- Enabling CI/CD with Docker & Kubernetes to containerize applications and orchestrate deployments for scaling.
- Developing and delivering features, leading daily scrums, conducting sprint planning and retrospectives while continuously collaborating with stakeholders, optimizing team performance and creating a culture of growth.

Advisory Software Engineer | Technical Lead | Scrum Master | IBM | Connections

Jan 2010 - Aug 2015

Led a global team of 10 developers, successfully delivering **multiple** product releases for IBM Connections. Primary achievements -

- Received Outstanding Achievement Award for leading successful integration of IBM Mail into Connections.
- Managed client crit-sits, driving open issues to closure and ensuring effective stakeholder communication.
- Developed robust RESTful APIs (JAVA), facilitating seamless frontend-backend data exchange and integration.
- Enabled full test coverage (Mocha), automation testing(Selenium) and continuous integration pipelines(Jenkins)
- Enhanced brand and market presence by publishing articles & delivering presentations at yearly IBM Conference.

Software Engineer II | IBM | Lotus Quickr

Oct 2008 - Dec 2010

- Developed customizable product themes and multiple portlet applications using Java, Javascript and Dojo.
- Implemented secure user session & cookie management, optimizing authentication and maintaining statefulness.
- Received UX Champion Award for increased customer satisfaction with continuous stakeholder engagement

Software Engineer | IBM | Document Manager and Forms

Oct 2004 - Dec 2008

- Developed Eclipse IDE wizard in Java to generate custom form instances(XML, XFORMS) for mobile rendering.
- Reduced support inquiries by publishing documentation and tutorials on application usage and features.

CAREER BREAK July 2018 - Present

A career pause for an expat relocation. Repatriated and excited to return to work.

- Project <u>Inspire</u>: A fullstack ecommerce React application to search and purchase items from a catalog. Integrated with mongoDB, NodeJS for serving APIs to manage data and Auth0 for user authentication.
- Project <u>Game-hub</u>, a responsive React application to find, sort & filter backend data.
 Integrated offline pages, error handling and a reusable HTTP service to retrieve backend data.
- Portfolio showcasing multiple fullstack, frontend, vanilla JS and CSS applications.
- Completed certifications: React 18; PMI Agile Foundations; Cert Prep: PMI Agile Practitioner

SKILLS

Technical: Java, React, Node.js, Javascript, ES6, JSON, HTML, CSS, SASS, Jest, Mocha, Selenium, Webpack, REST, PostgreSQL, MySQL, JIRA, Jenkins, Docker, Kubernetes; **Leadership:** Team Management, Stakeholder Management, Collaboration, Problem Solving, Adaptability, Team Work, Innovation, Agile Methodologies, Scrum, GitHub

EDUCATION

North Carolina State University, Bachelors in Computer Science (Summa Cum Laude)